Finding Aid for Department of Family Medicine (University of Michigan) records, 1971-2014
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Family Medicine (University of Michigan) records 1971-2014
University of Michigan. Department of Family Medicine.
2 linear feet
0589 Bimu 2
The University of Michigan Department of Family Medicine was founded as the Department of Family Practice in 1978. The department provides education to graduates in family medicine, operates family practice centers in Michigan as part of the residency program, and conducts research. Material includes accreditation reports, departmental reviews, annual reports, residency training material, and photographs and publications.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records were transferred to the Bentley Historical Library from the Department of Family Medicine (Donor no. 9554 ) beginning in January 2005.
The record group is open without restriction.
The University of Michigan Department of Family Medicine was founded as the Department of Family Practice in 1978. The first chair was Dr. Terence C. Davies. The department was established to improve the quality of primary health care through educating graduate students and conducting research.
The residency program is three years in duration. The residents work at the family practice centers operated by the department where they see patients and work as part of a team of residents and faculty members. The first center was opened in Chelsea, Michigan in 1978. Students can also chose to fulfill their residency at the center in Ypsilanti, Michigan opened in 1993.
Initially, the focus of the department was to establish the patient care practice and the residency program, as well as an undergraduate education program. Following the first department review in 1983, Dr. Davies shifted the focus of the faculty to also emphasize scholarly research. During this review, the University of Michigan confirmed its commitment to maintaining the department.
Dr. Davies stepped down as department chair in 1986. Dr. Thomas L. Schwenk was named interim chair and became chair in 1988. Under Dr. Schwenk, the department expanded, opening additional family practice centers in Ypsilanti, Dexter, and Ann Arbor, Michigan and moving existing practices into new facilities. The department also restructured the governance of the program. In 1997, the department's name was changed to the Department of Family Medicine to more accurately reflect the academic nature of the department. The program is now nationally well known and has been ranked in the top five in the nation by U.S. News & World Report from 2003 to 2005. Schwenk's tenure as chair ended in 2011. Philip Zazove became chair in 2011.
Chairs of the Department of Family Medicine
1978-1986 Terence C. Davies
1986-2011 Thomas L. Schwenk
2011- Philip Zazove
For additional information, see the department website: http://www.med.umich.edu/fammed
The Department of Family Medicine records document the founding and development of the department and the Chelsea Family Practice Center. The record group is divided into four series: Administrative Files, Topical Files, Photographs, Publications, and Archived Website.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Dept. of Family Medicine.; Family medicine--Study and teaching--Michigan.; Residents (Medicine); Family medicine.; Medicine--Study and teaching.; Schwenk, Thomas L.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Administrative Files
  The series Administrative Files (0.75 linear feet, 1971-2014) is comprised of papers related to the establishment and continued development of the program. It includes accreditation reports, department development plans, executive committee meeting minutes, papers of the committees on residency and research programs and the department review reports from 1983.
  - Accreditation Proposal II: Residency Training in Family Practice 1981 (Box 1)
  - Accreditation Proposal II: Residency Training in Family Practice 1981 (Box 1)
  - Activity Reports 1981-1988 (Box 1)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Medical Student Teaching in the Ambulatory Setting 1987 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports 1988-1992, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Annual Report Fiscal Year 1992 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1991-2004
    - General 1986-2001 (Box 1)
    - New endowments and donations 1991-2004 (Box 1)
  - Department Development Plans
    - Progress Report and Planning Overview 1978 (Box 1)
    - Projections and Plans for the Period 1981-1984 1981 (Box 1)
  - Department House Officers 1984-1998 (Box 1)
  - Department Reviews
    - 1983
      - External Review Correspondence 1984 (Box 1)
      - Internal Departmental Review Committee 1983 (Box 1)
      - Internal Review Report 1983 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee Meeting Minutes 2005-2014 (Box 1)
  - Family Practice Residency Planning Committee
    - Guidelines for Curriculum Development 1976 (Box 1)
    - Meeting Minutes 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - Report 1976 (Box 1)
  - Grant for Predoctoral Training in Primary Care 1997-2004 (Box 1)
  - Research Task Force Report 1982 (Box 1)
  - Residence Training Program Grant for Graduate Training in Family Medicine 1980 (Box 1)
- Topical Files 1972-2011
  Topical Files (0.5 linear feet, 1972-2011) includes papers related to the history of the department and the family practice centers operated by the department. The records of the department's history include newspaper articles as well as programs and speeches from anniversary celebrations. The majority of the family practice center papers are from the center in Chelsea and cover the decision to establish the center in the 1970s and the expansion of the facility in 1995.
  - Davies, Dr. Terence
    - Articles 1977-1990 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1978-1990 (Box 1)
  - Department Anniversaries
    - 5th Anniversary 1982 (Box 1)
    - 10th Anniversary 1988, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 20th Anniversary 1998 (Box 1)
    - 25th Anniversary 2003 (Box 1)
    - 30th Anniversary 2008 (Box 1)
    - Japanese Family Health Program 10th Anniversary 2004 (Box 1)
  - Department History
    - Departments Beginning's 1977-1979 (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan Medical Center Articles 1989-1995 (Box 2)
  - Department Statistics 2011 (Box 2)
  - Educational Programs and Courses 1998-1999 (Box 2)
  - Faculty Bibliography 1988-1998 (Box 2)
  - Family Medicine Health Clinics (Box 2)
    - Briarwood
    - Chelsea Family Practice Center
      - Brochures 1984, undated (Box 2)
      - Center Expansion 1994-1995 (Box 2)
      - Center Expansion Guestbook 1995 (Box 2)
      - Consultant Reports
        - Chelsea Medical Clinic Appraisal 1976 (Box 2)
        - Proposed Ambulatory Care Center Appraisal 1972 (Box 2)
        - Starting the Residency Program in Chelsea 1976 (Box 2)
      - Marketing and News Articles (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
      - Patient Information Book 1979 (Box 2)
    - Family Practice Providers undated (Box 2)
    - Stockbridge Family Practice 2000 (Box 2)
    - Ypsilanti Family Practice Providers (Box 2)
  - Family Practice Clerkships
    - Evaluations 1986-1998 (Box 2)
    - General 1978-2000 (Box 2)
  - Informational Booklet 1980 (Box 2)
    (includes photographs)
  - Marketing Materials (all clinics) (Box 2)
  - The Family Practitioner and the University of Michigan by Dr. Jeffrey Stross, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Symposium Series 1984 (Box 2)
  - Women's Health Day (Box 2)
- Photographs, 1978-2004
  Photographs (0.25 linear feet, 1978-2004) contains photographs of faculty, staff, students and the family practice center facilities. Of special note are photographs of doctors working with patients and photographs from the construction of the new Chelsea facility.
  - Doctors with Patients undated (Box 2)
  - Events 1987, 2004 (Box 2)
  - Facilities
    - Building Exteriors and Signs 1980s (Box 2)
    - Construction and Opening of the Chelsea Facility 1994-1996 (Box 2)
  - Faculty and Graduates 1978-1990 (Box 2)
  - Inauguration of George A. Dean, M.D. Chair in Family Medicine 2007, CD (Box 2)
  - Staff and Students undated (Box 2)
- Publications 1979-1988, 2006-2011
  Publications (0.25 linear feet, 1979-1998) is composed of newsletters and booklets published by the department. There are newsletters for alumni, staff and students, and patients at Chelsea Family Practice Center. The booklets are promotional material explaining the residency program and an instructional booklet for residency students.
  - Brochures (Box 2)
  - Newsletters
    - Department Newsletter (Box 2)
      - 1979-1984
      - 2006-2011
    - Department of Family Medicine Alumni Society Newsletter, 1985-1988, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Family Practice Center at Chelsea Newsletter, 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - Residency Program Booklets 1980-1997 (Box 2)
- Archived Website
  The Archived Website series, 2014-, documents the mission, activities, policies, and individuals involved in the operation of the Department of Family Medicine. Content includes information about the department’s clinical and educational programs, staff, and research activities. This archived website is hosted at http://webarchives.cdlib.org/a/universityofmichigan/.
  - 2014 -